https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xwtgByffoUw You know, to understand exchange rates, you really need to grasp one concept: foreign
Để hiểu về tỷ giá hối đoái (gọi tắt là tỷ giá), bạn cần phải hiểu khái niệm này: ngoại hối,
exchange, i.e., foreign money, is really just another commodity to be bought and sold. This
ví dụ như ngoại tệ, thực chất chỉ là một mặt hàng có thể mua và bán.
is where the term foreign exchange market comes from. It’s a market, so there must
Từ khái niệm trên ta có khái niệm thị trường ngoại hối. Đó là một thị trường, vì vậy
be those who want to buy the currency, and those who supply it.
phải có người muốn mua ngoại tệ, và phải có người cung cấp mặt hàng đó.
On the demand side, what reason (or reasons) could people possibly have to want to purchase
Ở phía cầu, lí do (hoặc những lí do) gì khiến người ta muốn mua
foreign exchange? Well, there are three major reasons really: First, people want foreign
ngoại tệ? Có ba lí do chính: Đầu tiên, ta muốn ngoại tệ
money for travel and tourism; second, foreign money is needed for trade, to buy foreign
để di chuyển và du lịch; thứ hai, ta cần ngoại tệ để buôn bán, để mua hàng và
goods and services; third, foreign money is needed for investment purposes, be it financial
các dịch vụ ngoại; thứ ba, ngoại tệ dùng vào những mục địch đầu tư, từ đầu tư kinh doanh,
investment, like purchase of foreign-denominated financial assets, or real investment, like
như mua những tài sản ngoại, đến đầu tư địa ốc,
building a new factory overseas. A change in any of these three components will alter
như xây nhà máy ở nước ngoài. Bất kì thay đổi gì ở ba yếu tố này đều ảnh hưởng
the demand for foreign exchange.
lượng cầu ngoại tệ.
For example, a lot of recent Hollywood blockbuster movies have been filmed in New Zealand; what
Ví dụ, gần đây Hollywood quay rất nhiều phim bom tấn ở New Zealand; điều gì
if this creates a sudden surge in tourists going to New Zealand? These tourists will
xảy ra nếu việc đó thôi thúc khách du lịch đến New Zealand? Họ sẽ
need New Zealand dollars, creating an increase in demand for that currency. Similarly, if
cần tiền đô New Zealand, làm lượng cầu tiền New Zealand tăng. Cũng thế, nếu
US companies decide they’d like to build factories in New Zealand (real investment),
công ty Mỹ quyết định xây nhà máy ở New Zealand (đầu tư địa ốc),
or purchase NZ$-denominated financial assets (financial investment), the demand for the
hoặc mua tài sản ở tiền đô NZ (đầu tư kinh doanh),
New Zealand dollar would increase.
lượng cầu đô New Zealand sẽ tăng.
Now let's go back to the idea of the foreign exchange market, with the New Zealand dollar
Quay lại khái niệm thị trường ngoại hối, ở đây đô New Zealand
being the foreign exchange. Initially, there is a certain supply of New Zealand dollars,
là ngoại hối. Ban đầu, có một lượng cung tiền đô NZ nhất định,
and a certain demand. The equilibrium price in this market is called the exchange rate.
Giá cân bằng của thị trường được gọi là tỷ giá.
OK; now let's throw the increase in demand for the New Zealand dollar into the picture.
Giờ hãy xét khi lượng cầu đô NZ tăng lên.
What happens to the value of the New Zealand dollar as more tourists travel there, or as
Giá đồng đô NZ sẽ như thế nào khi nhiều khách du lịch hơn, hoặc khi
more US companies invest? As with any commodity, when the demand for the New Zealand dollar
nhiều công ty Mỹ đầu tư? Giống như mọi mặt hàng khác, khi lượng cầu của đồng đô NZ
increases, its value increases. We see the exchange rate, in terms of the US dollar per
tăng, giá trị cũng sẽ tăng. Ta sẽ thấy tỷ giả của đồng đô la Mỹ so với
New Zealand dollar, increase. This is called an appreciation of the New Zealand dollar.
đồng đô la NZ tăng. Đây gọi là sự lên giá của đồng đô NZ.
When dealing with bilateral exchange rates like this one -- that is to say, the relative
Khi gặp tỷ giá song phương như vầy, - nghĩa là, giá trị tương đối
value of two currencies – it is necessarily the case that is one currency becomes stronger,
giữa hai loại tiền tệ - thì bắt buộc một loại tiền phải mạnh lên,
or more valuable, relative to the other -- in this case, the New Zealand dollar is increasing
hoặc tăng giá hơn loại tiền còn lại - Trường hợp này, đồng đô NZ đang tăng giá
in value relative to the US dollar -- the other currency is decreasing in value, or
so với đồng đô Mỹ - loại tiền còn lại sẽ giảm giá trị, hay mất giá.
depreciating. In this example, as the New Zealand dollar appreciates, the US dollar
Trường hợp này, đồng đô NZ càng lên giá, đồng đô Mỹ càng
is getting relatively weaker, or depreciating.
trở nên yếu đi, hoặc mất giá.
OK, so changes in demand for currency will affect the exchange rate. What about changes
Vậy thay đổi trong lượng cầu tiền sẽ ảnh hưởng đến tỷ giá. Vậy thay đổi
in supply? Well, ultimately who is it that controls the supply of foreign currency? The
về lượng cung thì sao? Cuối cùng thì ai kiểm soát lượng cung ngoại tệ?
foreign government. If the US wanted to drive the value of its own currency up, it would
Đó là chính phủ nước ngoài. Nếu Mỹ muốn tăng giá trị tiền tệ của nước mình lên, nước này
decrease the supply of dollars. If it wanted to drive value down, it would increase the
sẽ giảm lượng cung tiền. Nếu nước muốn làm mất giá tiền, Mỹ sẽ tăng lượng
supply of dollars. Why would a country one manipulate its own currency value?
cung tiền. Tại sao một nước lại muốn kiểm soát giá trị tiền tệ của mình?
Let me give you an example. Suppose you are a US furniture producer, and government protection
Để tôi đưa một ví dụ. Ví dụ bạn là một nhà sản xuất nội thất Mỹ, và chính phủ
for the spotted owl means you can’t get the lumber that you need domestically. So
bảo vệ loài cú lông đốm, nghĩa là bạn không thể lấy gỗ nội được.
you call up a Canadian lumber mill, tell them you’d like to place an order, and they tell
Vậy bạn gọi cho nhà máy cưa ở Canada, nói là bạn muốn đặt hàng, và họ báo giá
you that the lumber is going to cost CAN$50,000. I don’t know about you, but my bank account
là gỗ sẽ tốn 50,000 đô Canada. Tôi không biết bạn thì sao, nhưng tài khoản ngân hàng
doesn't happen to have any Canadian dollars in it. This is where the exchange rate comes
tôi không có tiền đô Canada. Đây chính là lúc sử dụng tới tỷ giá.
in. If I can figure out how much one Canadian dollar costs, then I can use that to calculate
Nếu tôi biết một đô Canada bằng bao nhiêu đô Mỹ, tôi có thể dùng tỷ giá đó để tính
how much 50,000 Canadian dollars will cost. The price of one Canadian dollar, in terms
cho 50,000 đô Canada. Giá của một đô Canada so với một đô Mỹ chính là
of US dollars, is the exchange rate (dollars per Canadian dollar). I checked the dollar
tỷ giá (đô Mỹ so với đô Canada). Tôi xem tỷ giá đô Mỹ
per Canadian dollar exchange rate for April 7, 2010 on x-rates.com, and found that CAN$1
so với đô Canada vào 7 tháng Tư, 2010 ở x-rates.com, và thấy rằng CAN$1
was equivalent to US$.998.
bằng với US$0.998.
Just as a side note, this nearly one-to-one parity between the two country’s currencies
Lưu ý rằng tỉ giá gần bằng 1:1 giữa hai loại tiền tệ của hai nước
is highly unusual. More on that in a minute.
là rất hiếm. Tôi sẽ nói về điều đó sau.
So if one Canadian dollar costs 99.8 cents US currency, how much will CAN$50,000 cost?
Vậy nếu một đô Canada bằng 0.998 đô Mỹ, 50,000 đô CAN bằng bao nhiêu?
In the end, it will cost you US$49,900 to purchase the Canadian lumber. Now let’s
Tóm lại, sẽ tốn US$49,900 để mua gỗ Canada. Giờ hãy
take a little trip back in time, and figure out how much that same C$50,000 worth of lumber
quay lại một vài năm, và tìm hiểu CAN$50,000 tiền gỗ
would've cost in April of each year for the previous 20 years. When would you most like
sẽ tốn bao nhiêu vào tháng Tư mỗi năm trong vòng 20 năm trước. Khi nào bạn
to have purchased that lumber? You can see by looking at the data, that when the foreign
sẽ muốn mua số gỗ nhất? Nhìn vào số liệu có thể thấy, đó là khi ngoại tệ rẻ nhất,
currency is the cheapest, in this case 2001, at $.64 per Canadian dollar, the foreign imports
ở đây là năm 2001, một đô Canada bằng 0.64 đô Mỹ, hàng nhập khẩu
are the cheapest -- US$32,000. Even if the Canadian lumber mill sees the same CAN$50,000
có giá rẻ nhất - US$32,000. Dùnhà máy cưa ở Canada chỉ thấy lượng gỗ đó với giá CAN$50,000
every year, the price to the US importer changes as the exchange rate changes. When the Canadian
mỗi năm, nhưng với Mỹ, giá nhập khẩu thay đổi theo tỷ giá. Khi đồng đô Canada
dollar depreciates, the lumber is cheaper, and US importers will buy more lumber. On
mất giá, tiền gỗ rẻ hơn, người Mỹ sẽ nhập nhiều gỗ hơn. Mặt khác,
the flip side, as the Canadian dollar depreciates, the US dollar is getting stronger relative
đồng đô Canada càng mất giá thì, so với đồng Canada, đồng đô Mỹ càng mạnh hơn
to the Canadian dollar, or it’s appreciating. While US consumers are enjoying a strong dollar
hay ta nói nó tăng giá. Người mua hàng ở Mỹ thì thích một đồng đô mạnh
and buying lots of Canadian goods, Canadians are seeing the US dollar, and therefore US
và mua nhiều hàng Canada hơn, còn người Canada thì thấy đồng đô Mỹ, và
goods, as more expensive. Canadians import fewer US products if the Canadian currency
hàng hóa Mỹ, càng đắt hơn. Canada nhập ít hàng Mỹ hơn nếu đồng đô Canada
is weak. A weak Canadian dollar is good for Canada's trade balance, as Canada's exports
yếu. Đồng đô Canada yếu lại tốt cho cán cân thương mại, vì hàng xuất khẩu
rise and imports fall. At the same time, the US trade balance gets worse -- we are importing
tăng còn hàng nhập giảm. Còn cán cân thương mại Mỹ thì tệ hơn - Mỹ đang nhập
more and exporting less.
quá nhiều và xuất khẩu quá ít.
The effect of the currency value on the trade balance takes me back to the question: why
Ảnh hưởng của giá tiền tệ lên cán cân thương mại đưa ta về câu hỏi ban đầu:
would a country want to manipulate its own currency value? You now know the answer to
tại sao một nước lại muốn kiểm soát giá trị tiền tệ của mình? Bạn giờ đã biết
this; if a country can keep its currency cheap, then it keeps its products cheap, and foreign
câu trả lơi; nếu một nước có tiền tệ giá thấp, thì nước đó có sản phẩm nội rẻ,
products expensive -- both of which are good for the balance of trade.
còn sản phẩm ngoại thì đắt - đều tốt cho cán cân thương mại.
The US has certainly been after China during the first decade of the 21st century; China
Suốt thập kỉ đầu thế kỉ 21, Mỹ luôn ở sau Trung Quốc vì Trung Quốc
keeps its currency value artificially low in order to keep favorable trade balance.
giữ đồng Nhân Dân Tệ thấp để thuận lợi về cán cân thương mại.
NEXT TIME: Comparative advantage and trade TRANSCRIPT00(MACRO) EPISODE 33: EXCHANGE RATES
BÀI TIẾP: Lợi thế so sánh và thương mại.